[Music]
n
hello good evening good day everybody
and welcome back to the ask abijit show
the latest episode number 226 I hope
you're all doing great so before we
begin let me uh let me see uh let me
greet those of you who are on the live
chat I can see two idiot nris from
Canada I can see padman go Swami I can
see dungar Singh Chan hello pan Kumar
Singh shagun chukra hello an
anur study log rwi fuy Cricket nishal Ry
Samsung Galaxy feminist Slayer hello
Barat first Sagar Shashi Kiran PR Paul
hello from Kolkata anant Pai GK B data
subo sarar flexible guy Sergeant skylin
Mr 88 misogynist Slayer Sid sidar Gupta
abiram
cherala abinav go abinav Pak Arjun
tripati vikash giri brown boy s Rahul
dun bipul Singh goami again sidhar Gupta
Krishna 14 mukund GES rikesh Das Gupta
rudra Arya abishek Sumit pal Dr Atul
arindam go joy Juma Joy o Juma sarak
Gupta Daria Lavan alok B Nandan patidar
netian Chan aradya shat Pur NRI
chaitanya
minini Blitz Ray YT Shashank saat ginta
Efron abinav Pak Vishnu Bohanan ramay
Raj Singh Priyanka javala debaron
bachara SSB party mavin nikit Singh satk
juu hello study Vlogs
rwi and who else who else uh J guman Jes
jigesh D Vishnu Moana
Gish Jack Jack hello
sir vikor Nandan J Raj
lit and so many more okay so I'm going
to take questions that you have asked in
the comments I have youve asked as
always hundreds of questions and I've
selected some 20 odd of th those
questions can't select all unfortunately
POS of time only two hours so I'll take
about 20 questions from the comments and
then I'll take the rest of the questions
if there is time from the uh live chat
uh and maybe I can take one question or
two okay I'll take that from the live
chat later let me take questions uh from
the that you asked in the comments so
let's begin with the first
question so this is by umax
870 the recent 2023 paper by Paul
hegerty has proven that the sarasti syu
civilization is indeed the Vic
civilization what are your thoughts on
this okay so does that paper actually do
that what is this paper let's take a
look at this paper where where is this
paper let's let's try and find this
paper do we have it somewhere yes I
think I have this paper language trees
so let's put that on the
screen so this is the paper that umax
870 is referring to language trees with
sampled ancestors support a hybrid model
for the origin of Indo European
languages and this is a pretty
uh compact paper I mean it's not exactly
compact but it's not extensive as in it
doesn't have dozens of pages and uh this
is the paper this is a PDF which is
available online okay it's available for
download in case you want to see it and
it says that uh it supports a hybrid
model for the origin of the Indo
European languages that's what this
paper says now I went through this paper
and what what does this paper say is
what we have to understand and what is
the context behind the paper what
problem is it referring to what open
issue or question is it referring to and
what are the uh findings of this paper
and does it actually prove that the
Saraswati Sindu civilization is indeed
the Vic civilization so the context of
the paper is the question of the origin
of the so-called Indo-European language
family this is a very extensive language
family of languages that are related to
each other you can see common words
vocabulary that is similar and has
origins in in obviously some previous
language and then so on so forth so
that's the indoeuropean language family
uh it was discovered by the Europeans
when they arrived in India a few
centuries ago and they were already
familiar with Greek and Latin and the
similarities between these two languages
and they noticed that Sanskrit is also
so very similar to Greek and Latin and
Sanskrit is older I mean now they claim
that that's that's a whole that's the
whole controversy so this is a language
family that is spoken by nearly half of
the global population the Indo European
language family so it's it's a matter of
obviously it's it's uh something that is
that a lot of people are interested in
to find out the origin of this family of
this language family now there are two
main hypothesis about the origin of the
Indo Indo European language family the
first is the step hypothesis so the step
hypothesis says that it suggests it
claims that the origin of the Indo
European language family could lie in
the pontic Caspian step about 6 and a
half thousand years before today and
it's associated with horse
riding uh Nomads horse B horse riding
pastoralists and that sort of people so
that's the step hypothesis and then
there's the Anatolian hypothesis so it
says that it it disagrees with the step
hypothesis and it says that U the this
language family is about 9,000 or so
years old and it's linked and it
originates in the so-called fertile
Cresent the uh Mesopotamia region and
it's linked to the spread of Agriculture
from this Fertile Crescent so it claims
that agriculture originates here and so
on so forth okay now this paper that we
spoke about okay what are the findings
of this paper let's put this paper back
back on the
screen what are the findings of this
paper or the conclusions so this paper
finds that the
estimated root age the estimated age of
origin of the Indo European language
family is about
8,120 years before today roughly with
with a range between 6,000 something and
9,000 something years so the median the
average is about 8,000 or so years so
this say this definitely predates the
timeline of the step hypothesis and it
it it suggests that there was rapid
early branching of this language family
into multiple major
subgroups now this this paper claims the
Anatolian branch of the Indo European
language family most likely originated
south of the Caucasus region not in the
step not in the Eurasian step but south
of the Caucasus region where South they
can't say but it originates south of the
Caucasus region and then there would
have been subsequent movements of this
language family northward that could
have established a secondary Homeland in
the Eurasian step so the primary
Homeland the origin it says is south of
the Caucasus that is a major uh
disagreement with the step
hypothesis uh so this this result aligns
with what they call a hybrid hypothesis
it integrates aspects of the Anatolian
hypothesis Anatolian origin model and
the step origin model but there is
initial dispersal of the language family
from south of the Caucasus and later
migration into the step which then
contributes to expansions of the
European languages the the European
branches of the Indo-European language
family okay so that's what this says it
doesn't speak about the sarasti Hindu
civilization or the the so-call harapan
civilization it doesn't really make
direct references to our ancient
civilization but it kind of perhaps
could allude to it by saying this
originated south of the Caucasus south
of the Caucasus you have many
geographical regions mainly Iran the
iranic region and of course India also
is south of the Caucasus but not
directly south it's southeast of the
Caucasus so um it's it's uh that's the
that's the approach they've taken and
that's the FI conclusions and findings
that that they have so it doesn't
directly prove as such specifically that
the sarasa Sindu civilization is The Vic
civilization that there is no there is
no reference to the Vic civilization or
the Saraswati Sindu civilization it only
speaks about the origin of the Indo
European language family and it says it
it originated south of the Caucasus
about 8,000 something years before today
that's what it says so let's not jump to
conclusions
uh we all have our favorite theories and
all that but uh we have to be very
factual when it comes to these
matters uh so this
is progress in this matter but I'm not
sure if we'll ever be able to
conclusively determine where this
language family originated and of course
uh the results are bound to be
controversial if such findings actually
happen so that's what I can say about
this matter
okay can you make a detailed video in
which you read a scientific research
paper of your choice in detail and
handhold and guidance on what things are
important what to look for and how to
understand the research paper well I
could do that but it would take a couple
of hours it would be a live stream of a
couple of hours and I'm not sure how
many people are actually interested in
this you know I mean I can spend two
hours of my time doing that and it would
be kind of
uh uh it would be an explanation of how
to think from first principles because
if I take a research paper in any
subject whether it's physics or or
genetics or or whatever uh I I have to
assume that most readers aren't familiar
with the topic and don't have any speal
specialized knowledge of the topic so
then I have to uh go deeper into first
principles thinking and explain what
this means in Lay person language and
how to understand what this means in Lay
person language which is a pretty
extensive kind of discussion I'm not not
sure how many people would actually be
interested in that I think if I would to
do were to do a live stream like that I
may have maybe 100 live viewers or
something maybe 50 not sure but if uh so
let me know know in the live chat in the
comments below if you are really
interested in this and maybe if enough
people are interested I could take that
up
yeah okay akan bat 69 says why do you
have a bias against Alexander and not
the Persians you said that Alexander
brutally conquered the persan Empire and
that he was a cruel ruler that was true
but how were the Persians any different
they were the ones to invade Greece in
the first place and they destroyed the
burned the city of Athens yeah Alexander
just took revenge on them okay yeah good
question I mean I I get where you coming
from now have you
studied the history of the AED Empire in
detail the hakar empire
and have you studied the actual history
of Alexander's
career if you have not I
mean so or have you just read a few
paragraphs here and there and then you
feel that I am biased look first of all
you to understand that everyone is
biased including me I have my biases I
am biased towards my country I'm biased
towards various things it is natural for
people to be biased and those who claim
to be unbiased are lying let's be very
clear about that so first first of all
there is that now secondly am I biased
you say that uh the the Persians uh
invaded Greece and destroyed Athens and
Alexander was taking Revenge fair enough
that is indeed the case but is that all
that is to the life and and career of
Alexander the Greek so see to understand
the proper context of something you need
to read in
detail you can't just uh draw your
conclusions based on what somebody said
or a couple of paragraphs or half a
chapter or one chapter he read
somewhere because most of the writings
about Alexander are simply geographies
in which they embellish his uh his
career and his achievements and glorify
his accomplishments but you need to take
a factual look at what Alexander did
through his career and um you don't need
to read an extensive book here is one
book let me zoom in in can I zoom in
okay I'm zooming out there let me show
you this this is a book it's it's called
Alexander the Great by Jacob Abbott and
this is a very uh very rapid very
concise uh outline of his career
okay and here and before I before I tell
you what Jacob Abbot writes about
Alexander let me give you a few
highlights of Alexander and's
career so first of all look it's not
about just taking Revenge when he was
establishing himself as the Top Dog in
Greece after the assassination of his
father Philip of Macedon Alexander had
to subjugate all potential rivals in
Greece and establish himself as the
Undisputed uh Overlord of Greece so what
he did was he besieged a city called
thieves in about 330 something a BC okay
he besieged this SE this city and uh
because because thieves sought to remain
independent and it kind of rebelled
against him so he besieged the city and
eventually The Siege was broken and
Alexander his troops were able to enter
the city and they destroyed the
city uh we don't know how many people of
the city were killed but we know that
about 30,000 or so
survived about 30,000 of these people
all those who survived most of them
including women and children were sold
into
slavery now what does this have to do
with Persia this is Alexander's actions
in Greece against Greek civilians
unarmed women and children he sold them
into slavery and the entire city was
systematically raised blocked by block
Brick by Brick to set an example to set
an example and to deter further
rebellions AB absolute cruelty so he
spared some people he spared those who
he was sure that had not participated in
the Rebellion but everybody else was
either killed or sold into slavery at
least 30,000 people were sold into
slavery mainly women and
children there wouldn't be so many that
many surviving males after the defeat of
Thieves that's one example of what he
did to his own people okay now later
after he decided to uh to invade East I
mean invade Asia
so and before he fought at Goa against
Theos II and so on before Persia he
besieged the city of Ty would you like
to see where Ty is let me show you where
Ty is okay uh so let's let's find out
where the city of Ty is let's go to the
map let's put the map on the screen I'll
show you where this
happened the city of of Tyre it's on the
eastern shore of the
Mediterranean okay and it still exists
there there's still a place called tire
and let's look at the satellite
imagery as you can see there's a small
Peninsula like thing that juts out over
here it was once an
island this was once an island and
eventually this this land was reclaimed
who so this was there was a fortress on
this island and it was a few hundred
meters out at Sea and this Fortress was
well defended and Alex it it served um
as from Alexander's perspective it was a
thorn in his flesh and he wanted to take
this city and this Fortress before he uh
went to Egypt if I'm not mistaken
chronologically so he besieged the city
of Ty okay and the siege of Ty lasted
about seven months he and his uh men
repeatedly tried to build
Bridges uh to the to the island and
these Bridges were repeatedly broken
down by the Defenders of the city and he
got more and more frustrated The Siege
lasted seven months and eventually he
captured the
city so during The Siege we don't know
how many people how many Defenders died
maybe several thousand Defenders of the
city were killed during the The Siege
over the course of fighting but after he
captured the city he crucified he
crucified everybody he could find and he
crucified them along the
shoreline as a warning to anybody who
would in the future dare to resist him
and once again the women and children
were sold into
slavery so he crucified all the men
sever 100,000 men he put them he
crucified them all along the coast and
the women and children were sold into
slavery these are all factual matters no
historian can deny these matters okay
this is all matter of
record then let's go to persis So
eventually um he reaches
Persia and uh okay so I'm not sure where
pers is I'll not try and find it on the
map let's put the map off the screen for
now
okay So eventually he um after taking
Egypt he fights against the Persians
against daras II and he defeats the
dasas dasas goes on the run for a few
months for a couple of years whatever
time it was and Alexander takes the
capital city of Persia parur it's called
persopolis today the Persians today call
it parsa its original name was
parur so this Capital City he takes it
and he has a great party in the city
drunken party and at night after getting
sufficiently drunk he orders the city to
be burned so the entire city was burned
a great great civilizational capital of
the Persian civilization of the Persian
Empire was burned and this was
allegedly in Revenge for the Persian
burning of Athens during the previous
Greco Persian Wars
so if it was just about revenge he would
have been satisfied with the burning of
parur persis but his actions go Way
Beyond Revenge I mean what was the need
to crucify thousands of people along in
the city of Ty why did he have to sell
women and children into slavery in
Greece in thieves in tire and this is
something he does repeatedly over and
over again he's Barbarian he's cruel his
campaign his throughout his conquests he
repeatedly enslaved large portions of
feed populations okay and these actions
they targeted civilians especially women
and children uh in thieves in in Tire in
persopolis he employed Terror tactics as
a deliberate strategy to intimidate and
subdue his opponents so when he was done
with Persia he wanted to conquer India
so there is this region between Persia
and India the baluchistan kind of region
which is kind of culturally both
cultures civilizations so um as he went
towards the indust river he would
capture small towns Villages and he
would execute the natives the
inhabitants completely all of them lots
of crucification lots of executions
there would be brahans who would refuse
to cooperate with him and tell him about
whatever information he wanted he would
crucify them he would talk torture them
he would have them tortured public
executions brutal punishments Etc
repeatedly over and over again burning
entire Villages and their populations
alive destroying crops destroying
infrastructure destroying settlements
and so on so the there was no limit to
this guy's cruelty Alexander okay and
wherever he conquered he imposed the
Greek culture the Greek language and
Greek governance on the conquered region
I mean look at what he did to Egypt most
people think that Egypt was U Egypt lost
its its cultural identity as a
consequence of the Roman occupation
which was done by Julius Caesar and Mark
Anthony Etc we not go there but Greece
uh it was it was Alexander who started
this this entire process he conquered uh
he walked into Egypt without really
having to fight yeah the Egyptians were
under the Persians and they thought that
he's a liberating liberating uh he's
liberating us but it they ended up being
enslaved by him right so heo he
appointed he he appointed a governor of
Egypt his name was toy and that was the
beginning of the toic Empire empire in
Greece and Greece in Persia I what am I
saying in Egypt and Egypt became very
rapidly heniz after that Cleopatra Queen
Cleopatra was entirely Greek he wasn't
Egyptian she wasn't African she was
Greek and so on so um that's the kind of
of career Alexander had terrible
terrible treatment of people enslavement
death the the and and there was violence
against women during his conquest of
various cities sexual violence against
women was Common Place women were
frequently taken as Spoils of War by his
soldiers and enslaved women faced
systematic abuse
so um so if you look at what he did he
was a great conqueror he failed
obviously in India Was Defeated and
probably that cost him his life but his
his conquests in other parts of the
world from from Macedonia all the way to
Persia they spread Greek culture
helenistic culture and ideas okay but
they came at the cost of immense human
suffering and tremendous
destruction and if you look at it from
today's perspective under current
International so-called international
law like the Geneva Convention Etc all
of this would be classified as war
crimes and crimes against humanity now
I'm not saying that the Persians were
were all all you know they they did not
do any such things but what Alexander
did was had nothing to do with revenge
against the persans now let me read the
last paragraph of this book written by J
Jacob Abbott
okay so the last paragraph Alexander
earned well the name and reputation of
the great he was truly great in all
those powers and capacities that can
Elevate one man above his fellows we
cannot help applauding the extraordinary
energy of his genius though we condemn
the selfish and cruel ends to which his
life was devoted he was simply a robber
but yet a robber on so vast a scale that
mankind in contemplating his career has
generally lost sight of the wickedness
of his crimes in their admiration of the
enormous magnitude of the scale on which
they were perpetrated that's the last
paragraph the concluding paragraph of
this book by Jacob Abbott so is Jacob
Abbott also biased against Alexander you
have to read history you to study
history in the full perspect in in the
full context you don't understand the
full context of what you're reading you
cannot simply
uh absorb the opinions of others and
what they say the whole world glorifies
Alexander because the whole world sees
history from a eurocentric
perspective and they see persan the
Persians as as if you watch movies made
about Alexander they will so show
persons as as a Rabel of ill coordinated
men who
look definitely definitively inferior to
the Greeks and so on that's the
perspective that they the subtly put
forth and that's is that's something we
are swallowing wholesale we have to
think
critically this has I have no bias
against anybody from this perspect in
this matter Alexander wasn't Indian
neither were the Persians how do I care
I'm not biased against anybody in this
matter when it comes to issues of the
national interest I'm biased towards
India no question about it but in this
matter how do I
care U so that's that's the deal okay
Alexander was truly Wicked according to
Jacob Albert and if you look at his
career fact actually you you cannot deny
it but probably most of us we don't do
it we look at what people write one
paragraph here one paragraph there
summarizing his life and his career and
we think oh is great and then why is
this abijit chaa guy saying bad things
about Alexander he must be biased please
please take some time to study things
properly okay Imran naimi says was Ahmed
sha abdali a pashon he never claimed to
be pashon according into writings and he
primarily used the Persian and turkic
languages in court his mother was named
nazu Ana and he called her nazu ana ana
means mother in turkic
languages he also called his wife beum
which is also a turkic word for wife and
his sons also had turkic names including
his first son timour which means iron in
the turkic languages there are also some
writings from abdali that are written in
the in the chagatai tur language and his
wife was a chagatai Turk given these
facts he's a Turk so why are historians
coning this
fact interesting question now I do not
claim to be any sort of authority on the
history of Afghanistan of the of the
Gandara region after the turkic
invasions okay the way I see it and the
way we should all see it is that U
Afghanistan was the original Kashmir
what you see today happening today in
Kashmir or in the past few decades is
what originally happened in Afghanistan
Afghanistan or gandar was the first
region of the Indian civilization that
that fell to the Turks after significant
uh resistance so it's natural for
turkic culture turkic language languages
and turkey DNA to enter Afghan U Society
if you look at Afghanistan today it's an
ethnic cocktail a mix of various ethnic
groups the primary ethnic group is what
are to is what called the pashun the
patan or pashon people they are the
primary ethnic group the Maj majority
population but you also have usbek you
also have hazaras you also have turkman
you also have tajiks who are Indo
Iranian people and so on so forth lots
of turkic uh population groups exist in
Afghanistan today and that's a
consequence of the invasions that
happened roughly a thousand years ago
now um Ahmed sha abdali also known as
Ahad durani he is recognized or he is
regarded as the father the founder of
the durani empire and the founder or the
father of the modern state of
Afghanistan now he was born into the
abdali tribe which was a pashon tribal
Confederation just like just like today
you call a whole bunch of people in
India rajputs but a thousand years ago
their ancestors would not even have have
used the word rajput right it's it's a
term that came that that originated much
later similarly a thousand years ago I
don't think any of the Afghans called
themselves
pashun that term probably emerged later
as an ethnic term in opposition to the
ones who were invading and occupying our
territory that sort of
thing um so so coming back to am abdali
he was born into the abdali tribe which
is a Pon tribal Confederation and he was
from the sadzi CL Clan of the popal zai
lineage of the abdal and the is are now
called the duris so so many rulers in in
Afghanistan in this region they used
persan as a court language because
persan had Prestige and it was wide
widely used the same thing you saw in
India as well in India when the the the
Turks ruled over India the so-called
mugal
Dynasty uh they also used persan as the
court language initially it was the
chagatai language or when when you when
you talk about the original Invaders was
who was the original Invader was it
zahin Babar it was zahin Babar right so
he spoke chakat but eventually his
descendants adopted the portion language
similar similarly the same happened in
Afghanistan so there was widespread use
of the persan language especially in the
courts so uh so Afghans the duris ETC
abdal they would they used these foreign
languages regardless of their ethnic
background so um Ahmed sh abdali he came
to power in the middle of the 18th
century in Afghanistan and he uh he was
originally called Ahmed Khan and he then
adopted the title Ahmed sha and he
adopted the the the the the epit
Duran which is Pearl of
pearls and he he changed the name of his
clan or tribe from abdali to
durani now this change doesn't reflect a
change in ethnicity but it was rather a
political move to consolidate power and
create a new identity for himself and
his tribe and his
Empire and when it comes to using turkic
words it's probably because the Turks
ruled over Afghanistan for such a long
time and and these words they just
infiltrated into the language there are
so many turkic words in Hindi today that
most Indians aren't even aware of so
many I will not go into the words what
the words are there are lots of words
from the turkic languages that are used
in Indian Indian languages like
Hindi what what does mean
means liver chiger means
liver in
Turkish what does mulim mean in Turkish
it means Bland or smooth and so on there
so many words that seem to be part of
Hindi but originate in turkic languages
and the same definitely applies to
Afghanistan as well uh so you would have
Turkish wordss you you will have Turkish
words that you ref use to refer to your
family members and whatnot I'm sure so
this this happened as a consequence of
the invasion turkic Invasion and
occupation of the subcontinent starting
with gandar Afghanistan the name Timur
for his son well you have Indians
calling their sons Timur these days
tamur right uh in in memory of the great
Barbarian great murderer mass murderer
Timur theame Tim L yeah so that doesn't
necessarily indicate turkic
ancestry and the word Timor the turkic
word
Timur it originates in the Sanskrit word
Chim which means iron so dwell on that
for a minute so what I'm trying to say
is that we have no conclusive evidence
that Ahmed Shah abdali had turkic
ancestry maybe he married a turkic lady
maybe his wife was was turkic maybe his
desc are half turkic that way I think
most Afghans by now would have some
amount of turkic ancestry purely from
the perspective because of the fact that
they the region was ruled over it was
invaded occupied and ruled over by Turks
for a very long
time so it's possible that he may have
had some turkic ancestry but to say that
he was entirely 100% turkic I personally
haven't found
evidence that supports this so I would
say maybe but I can't say for sure but
it looks like he may probably have been
a Pon okay I may be wrong but looks like
that sakra says why do we know little to
nothing about the pre-islamic history of
baluchistan and the baluch people why
does nobody discuss the Balo Hindus and
how the arabization and islamization of
balistan and the Balo people occurred I
couldn't find any books or articles on
this topic okay let's talk about
baluchistan let's put baluchistan on the
map for a bit so baluchistan is part of
the western western regions of the
subcontinent currently uh it's split
between uh Pakistan and Persia Pakistan
and Iran half of it roughly is in
Pakistan half of it roughly is in uh
Iran now yeah we look there are so many
regions of India about which we don't
know we know very little books aren
nobody cares to write books about that
nobody cares to delve into the
detailed history of the region and so on
so that's just the sad reality of of uh
the way we have approached our history
but I can tell you a few things um so
this
region used to be the the boundary or or
the
dividing region between India and Persia
it's kind of still is Pakistan is
temporarily Pakistan but it's in
territory historically and eventually so
uh and no disrespect to our Pakistani
friends who may be watching you are you
you are our people so
baluchistan at at times it was under
Persia at times it was under various
Indian Empires and kingdoms sometimes it
was split between the two and that sort
of thing and there used to be a kingdom
called the Indo parthian
Kingdom about 2,000 years ago in this
region before Indo parthan Kingdom you
had the AED Empire the hak Empire and
the morian Empire and so on yeah uh and
the two never really ever came into
conflict so bistan is that region it's
the Borderlands of both civilizations
India and Persia so after the collapse
of the uh ained Empire because of the
Greek Invasion Alexander's Invasion the
various Governors that appointed in
various territories they became
self-governing and they became small
Kings in their on the right and that's
how the Indo parthian Kingdom
emerged that's roughly 2,000 years ago
and the founder of the Indo parthian
kingdom was a king called
gfur the Greeks called him gondo FIS or
something let's let's let's uh Google
that Indo parthian
Kingdom uh let's put that on the screen
Indo parthan Kingdom
so here we have this Indo paan Kingdom
if we go to wikip all as always
Wikipedia is not 100% reliable not it is
not a necessarily reliable source of
information but let's just quickly take
a look at this so 19 ad to 226 ad it was
found by see it says gondes his name was
gaafer gaafer and this is what he looked
like this is his coin so this
Kingdom as you can see it ruled over
this region most of baluchistan and some
parts of gandhar as well and the
successor Kingdom of this was the parar
Raju
Kingdom now does it say the successors
are the parat okay here it is the parat
Raj so the parat Raj kingdom was a
dynasty of Paran Kings once again parat
Raj right the kings of
parata uh from 125 CE to about 300 CE
and if you look at the parat rajas and
we go to Google
parat rajas and we Google that and if
you look at the images you will see
their coinage so this is one of their
kings and if you see this coin as you
can see it's very
clearly U you can see the swastika right
away most of their coins had
swastikas as you can see lots of coins
with swas on that and you
have what is either brami or kosi script
I can't see from here looks like kosi
probably and so on so yeah yeah this
these are coins of the parat rajas and
these are the ancestors of today's baloi
people and you can you can look into
that I'll not go into further detail
about this uh but uh you have the Indo
parthan uh Kingdom and then you had the
parat rajas and the Indo Paran kingdom
was founded by
gfur not gondo feries but
gaafer look into do some research about
this it's very interesting then
eventually you had the invasions of the
Arabs
uh what was that guy's
name I forget the name of the Invader ah
Muhammad bin kasum right so he invaded
baluchistan and then sin then that's how
the process of arabization islamization
starts and and then you know how it goes
so that's in very brief about the older
history of baluchistan of what we now
call call baluchistan and the people of
bistan today are as we know under
tremendous subjugation and oppression by
Pakistan sadly uh
they are very much Indi of in Indian
people they live on both sides of the
Border in Pakistan as well as Persia
they speak their own language which is
an Indo Aran language and the language
is similar to to Cindi and Gujarati and
their Customs are also similar to Cindi
and Gujarati Customs so that is about
the buoi
people PR Paul says you mentioned in the
first episode of understanding America
how the Spanish people were astonished
by how healthy the natives of the
Americas were um the Caribbean region I
also noticed that figures like the
Vikings or Columbus seem to live
relatively short lives how was no was
this short life expectancy a common
issue across Europe during that period
or was it specific to certain groups
what were the main causes behind such
limited
lifespans um so when the uh when the
panat first came first reached the
Americas and saw the natives they were
astonished like you say and I mentioned
this in the first episode they were
astonished to see how healthy the
natives were the natives were tall
people compared to the Europeans the
Europeans were short the natives were
tall the natives were muscular the span
were not and the natives were mostly
almost naked and they had great skin
great uh oral great
health but they did not have swords and
iron and they did not have that
murderous attitude that the Spaniards
had
uh and the writer of the book that I'm
referring to and other writers as well
say that the Europeans were filthy many
Europeans did not ever bathe in their
whole
lifetime I mean I'm not making it up
read the
books and uh and there's a whole lot
more so it looks like European Customs
were such that uh hygiene was not
prioritized surprise
surprise uh imagine the smell I would
say but yeah European customs of the
time were such that high was not
prioritized bathing was unheard of and
uh and that obviously will will cause
health issues and a shorter
lifespan
um some of it would be because of the
cold climate in northern Europe so one
could understand if the Vikings did not
bathe frequently because the
temperatures are usually frigid in
Scandinavia uh so yeah that would be
that would act as so the temperature
would act as a deterrent against bathing
frequently but when it comes to Spain
it's not that cold it's a reasonably
Pleasant climate in Spain it's doesn't
freeze very frequently there it's
usually pretty warm and bommy climate so
why did the Spaniards insist on not
bathing and why were they so filthy uh
compared to the Indians we compared to
the the Indians as in the natives of the
Americas I don't know I don't know what
the culture cultural aspects were but
that's just what we know so I think this
was U not limited to to specific
European groups I think it looks like it
was it was common across Europe to not
bathe into and to have very questionable
standards of hygiene and that would
obviously uh cause life expectancy to
not be that that great in Europe and you
can see other examples and other
evidence of this I mean the black death
which was an epidemic of the bubonic
plague
it originated in China and eventually
made its way all across Eurasia all the
way to Europe all the way to the
westernmost parts of Europe and it
spread because of
Filth it spread because European cities
towns Villages were so filthy you would
have rats everywhere and the rat rats
everywhere and the Rats were
the were the carriers of the ticks with
which were the vectors of the
disease now it's astonishing that the
Black Death the Bubonic plague traveled
all the way from China all the way to
Western Europe the Western most part of
Europe and completely bypassed India how
does that happen India and China have
always had great
contacts lots of trade lots of cultural
relations lots of people to people
relations back in the day I'm not
talking about today historically so how
did the Black Plague the Bubonic plague
completely bypass India because India
had different different standards of
hygiene compared to Europe so it was
very easy to for for the plague to
proliferate in Europe but it simply
couldn't gain a footing in India
eventually you had plague epidemics in
India under British occupation where
Indians were no longer free to live
their lifestyle as per as as they used
to so I think it was a lifestyle Choice
it was a cultural I don't know if it's
culture if it's lifestyle today Europe
is very clean but it wasn't that way in
the
past uh the feminist Slayer says why are
Indian origin people playing for the US
cricket team whether male female of or
under 19 and so on white players who are
previously part of other countries or
played for other countries are also
representing the US why not Americans
themselves interesting question it has
to do with culture it has to do with
history and so on so we know that the US
the United States was the original
Founders were were uh English English
people British right and they this game
of Cricket came from England from
Britain so in the 18th and 19th
centuries cricket was played in the US
it was pretty popular it was widespread
until the first half roughly of the 19th
century and used to have Cricket played
everywhere lots of cricket games now
then you have the Civil War era during
which time which is the middle of the
19th century and during this time
baseball emerged as a very popular game
and it quickly replaced Cricket in
popularity and it especially became a
craze in New York and baseball came to
be known as the national Pastime and
Cricket continued to be played in the US
but it soon became a game that was
played by a minority the the high High
Society people high class people and
baseball was the game of the masses and
eventually Cricket essentially became
um died a slow death in the
US um and baseball became the national
Pastime and and the biggest game in the
US so uh that's the brief history of
cricket in the US now with in the 20th
century and 21st
century you had lots of um migrants
coming to the US
and becoming US citizens um and lots of
these came from the Indian
subcontinent whether it's India Pakistan
Sri Lanka whatever and
they continued playing Cricket I mean
Indians love Cricket so migrants who
went there and settled down and became
citizens they continued playing cricket
and that gave rise to lots of cricket
clubs and all that so it's mostly people
from the subcontinent because we are a
gigantic population group over here in
the subcontinent not in the US so it's
subcontinental mainly who uh play
cricket in the US and the these are many
of them are US citizens so that's why
the US has a national cricket team
whether it's under 19s or men's cricket
team or women's cricket team it's mainly
populated by uh subc Continentals mainly
Indians you also have former players
from other countries uh who was it I I
the last Cricket World Cup the last T20
World Cup I saw the US cricket team
there was this left arm fast bowler who
was of Indian origin who is a software
engineer he was he performed really
well um maharashtrian guy marati name I
forget his name right now my apologies
to him I was really impressed by his
perform with his performance um and
former West Indies players like Anderson
cumins ET have have played for the US
and uh I think who was that guy from New
Zealand the guy who hit the fastest ever
uh T20 Century I forget his Anderson
Corey Anderson I think he was playing
for the US this time so yeah look the US
is is the land of
opportunity and uh I think yeah one of
the Indian left arm Spinners a sick guy
who's now in his 30s uh he played for
the Indian under 19 under 19 team in the
world cup he was also represent in the
US so the US is the land of opportunity
and uh yeah they have a they have
multiple cricket teams now I think
they're going to have uh their version
of the IPL as well soon it's going to be
called I don't know what Yan PL or uspl
I don't know what it'll be called but
yeah so uh so yeah that's the deal
that's the history of cricket in the US
and that's the situation right now it's
mainly played by subcontinental I don't
think the the um the pure the the proper
Americans per se have too much of an
interesting Cricket they regard it as
more of a curiosity what what is going
on that sort of thing but yeah there you
have
it Rohan B says since all atoms are 99%
empty space therefore all the matter
that we see is also 99% empty space then
why is everything not
transparent yes atoms are mostly they
seem to be empty space right atoms seem
to be mostly empty space uh the solar
system is mostly empty space way more
than 9 99% % and if solar the solar
system and other star systems are mostly
empty space it means the Milky Way
galaxy is mostly empty space which means
the entirety of the universe is
overall almost all of it is just empty
space
right that's the context but coming back
to the question about atoms yeah it's a
very interesting question very
fascinating question that kind of helps
us uh drill down into the fundamentals
of physics and Quant physics so this
notion this idea that atoms are 99% plus
empty space it's a misconception it's a
very common Mis misconception which
which originates from originates in
outdated Atomic models so you had the
Solar System model of the atom there's
there's the nucleus at the center and
the electrons are going in circles or
ellipses around the nucleus just like
the planets orbit the Sun
so that is one model that that's the
model that students mainly think of
usually think of when they think of an
atom and we know that the nucleus is so
small and the electrons are even smaller
so it's mostly empty spaces so that's
that's an outdated atomic
model that is very that's the first
thing that's taught to students of
science which helps you
visualize the atom in your mind but it's
not
accurate so in reality atoms are not as
empty as this this idea suggests and
there are let me give you the reasons
why uh atoms are not really empty and
why objects are not transparent so in
atoms you have electron clouds and
electromagnetic fields atoms are have a
nucleus and we kind of know that the
nucleus is is the at the center of the
atom and these nuclei the nucleus of the
atom it's surrounded by clouds of
electrons when you talk about the
hydrogen atom is just one electron but
in most atoms oxygen iron uranium
whatever you have clouds of
electrons so these nuclei are surrounded
by clouds of electrons that occupy a
significant volume a certain amount of
volume these clouds are not empty space
these are regions where electrons are
likely to be found and the probability
of finding the electron depends on the
wave function which is quantum mechanics
I'll not discuss that these electrons
are all moving around and they generate
electromagnetic
fields described by the Maxwell
equations
so these electromagnetic fields fill the
space within and around
atoms and they interact with incoming
light waves so it's not exactly empty
space okay from from this perspective
now let's talk about quantum mechanics
and the behavior of electrons so in
quantum mechanics electrons don't behave
like discrete particles it's not a it's
not a billiard ball okay they don't
behave like discret discrete particles
orbiting the nucleus they exist in
probability distributions and these
probability distributions are called
orbitals these orbitals they effect okay
let me show you hydrogen atom orbitals
since we are discussing orbitals
interesting what I end up talking about
hydrogen
orbitals uh where's the screen let's
let's put that on the screen the are
these are Atomic orbitals they derived
from Solutions of the schinger equation
so this is the hydrogen wave function
and so on these are what the orbitals
look like and these do not represent
empty space these
uh these orbitals are probability
distributions where you have various
probabilities of finding these electrons
so there is no truly empty area in these
orbitals okay let's let's uh understand
that now so from that perspective from
the orbital model from the orbital
visualization you can see there is no
real empty space in these uh
atoms now let's talk about the
interaction of light with matter because
the question is about transparency right
so when light what is light light is
photons photons are waves as well as
particles let's talk about photons as
particles for a bit so when these
photons when light which is made of
photons it encounters M matter it
interacts with the electrons in the
atoms in various ways one of the ways is
absorption so electrons can absorb
photons depending on the energy of
depending on the frequency or wavelength
of the photon and if an electron absorbs
a photon it transitions to a higher
energy State it's called a Quantum jump
you know kollo that's one thing that can
happen in which case the the light that
light Quantum is
absorbed by the atom and it doesn't
reflect it right another way light can
uh interact with matter is by scattering
so it can be scattered by electrons
which changes the direction of the light
of the photon and then there is
reemission so absorbed energy absorbed
photons can be reemitted as light which
can happen at different at different
wavelengths so these interactions they
prevent light from Simply passing
through most materials
unimpeded then you have uh
density of of matter and material
properties the transparency of material
depends on its density and the
properties the the structure the atomic
and molecular structure of the material
so solids typically have tightly packed
atoms which increases the likelihood of
light matter interactions which
increases the likelihood of absorption
or scattering or something liquids have
more they are less dense than solids
which allows more light transmission and
gases are the least dense of the states
of matter will not go into plasma
so that's why air and many gases appear
transparent or
translucent transparency also depends on
the wavelength of the light okay so
visible light interacts strongly with
many many materials which makes them
opaque or
reflective x-rays are a whole different
matter and so on so all of these effects
put together ensure that most matter is
not
transparent um so yeah it all boils down
to quantum mechanics and the U way that
light interacts with atoms essentially
the way light photons interact with
electrons of an
atom Aima says two questions but
interrelated firstly are the yamnaya
people part of The Expelled tribes of
the vidc society secondly are the Greeks
one of the Lost tribes of the Vic
Wars okay uh let's talk about the Greeks
first and then we'll go to the YN
so the Greeks if you if you ask Shri
talageri who's one of the great
linguistic Scholars that we have then
the Greeks are descendants of a tribe
that was expelled out of India not tribe
I don't like this word tribe it's it's
Clans a tribe what is what is a tribe
and what's a clan a tribe is a small
group of people maybe 5200 or 150 or
let's say 500,000 people who live
isolated from other human societies
that's a tribe A Clan is simply a group
of people who are inter who are related
related to each other in some way
cousins and extended family and all that
so uh let us search search for what
talageri has to say
talageri Alina okay let's put this on
the screen okay let us see what Shri
tagiri has to say through his linguistic
research okay so the identity of the
enemies of
sudas in the Thea battle in the Riga the
battle of the 10
Kings and there were more than 10 Kings
by the way okay so uh it is one guy
against more than 10 so against a whole
Coalition of uh various
Clans so this is the earliest known
geopolitical event in recorded history
the earliest recorded battle in all of
literature the battle of the 10 kings in
the Riga and it is King sudas Who
belongs to the
bhata uh Confederation or the barata
lineage fighting against uh this entire
confederation so who are the who are the
uh who who are his opponents who are his
enemies so let's take a look at the
list simu bgu Paka balana Alina Sha
vishin paru or par pru or parava Dasa
Anu and so on and he identifies these
various tribe these these uh
Clans and he's able to show that the
simu are the Sima the Dasa are the dahi
the vishin are the nuristani or pachin
people the the Paka people are the pakun
the or the ancestors of the pakun uh the
Balan are the ancestors of of the
baluchi or Bolan people the partha or
the pru people are the ancestors of the
parthan or the partha people the parwa
clan is the ancestor of the Persians the
parha obviously Nam madra are the
ancestor of the medi
medians the Shiva tribe are the ancestor
of the K people of usbekistan the Dasa
are the dahai of West turkistan the simu
are the sarmatians the Alina are the
Allens and the Helen in the
helin the island uh were a nomadic
Iranian origin tribe according to
Western historians who eventually ended
up in
Spain and
uh became the iberians the
Spanish and the Alina eventually
according to talageri became the helenic
people the helin who are the Greeks
helas right right so according to
talageri the Alina people the Alina Clan
which was defeated which is one of the
clans of the Confederation that was
defeated by sudas it was expelled out of
India the Alina eventually became the
helenic peoples of of
Greece so yes from this linguistic
analysis perspective the Greeks are not
an ex a lost tribe of the Vic uh War but
one of the tribes
one of the Clans that was part of the
Confederation that was defeated in the
battle of the 10 plus Kings now coming
to the this question this question here
the yam people are they also part of The
Expelled tribes or The Expelled Clans we
don't know because we don't
know see we call them the yam why do we
call them the yam because the word yamna
means pit in Russian a pit a pit in the
ground and they found these Graves and
pits so they were called so they
eventually ended up being called the yam
from the Russian word for pit it doesn't
mean that they 5,000 years ago called
themselves yam it doesn't mean that we
don't know what they call themselves and
if we don't know what they call
themselves then we don't know how to
classify them whether to whether they
can be classified as one of these
expelled Clans the defeated Clans so we
don't know genetically we know that what
they look like we know what what
their what their major patrilineal h
group was lineage was it was r1b we
Indians most of us are
r1a they are a sister sister H group r1b
but you have r1b in India as well uh as
you go westwards from India towards EUR
towards Europe the frequency of r1b in
the population increases more and more
and more and more of course there are
regions where you have significant r1a
like U Germany Ukraine Russia Etc and
and obviously the Indian subcontinent
very strange but not maybe not that
strange uh so the yam are ARB most of
them um we know what they looked like
they were all tall guys tall muscular
guys uh tall as in like 6 feet roughly 5
510 5'11 6 feet was their average height
they were all muscular they had a high
protein diet mostly milk
and we know that they had dark hair and
dark and brown
eyes and we know that they had light
brown skin not white they were darker
than the average European today but they
had but they were not dark brown they
were light
brown so that's what we know the Yuma
looked like but we don't know whether
they we can classify them as we can we
can identify them as one of the expelled
Clans that was defeated in the
Battle of the 10 Kings so that right now
information or data we don't
have gorov says what do you think of the
recent development from ISRO that is
docking two satellites in space why is
India pursuing uh trying to have its own
ISS you mean space station by 2035 okay
so uh has it already happened I I know
that the launch happened of two
satellites that will dock in space has
it already happened I'm not sure I'm not
I'm not aware of that but I'm glad is
doing this it's an important
technological feat to achieve and it's
important that we know how to do this
and we can do this on demand whenever
required what does it mean it means you
have two satellites floating in space in
orbit not floating in space but orbiting
the Earth in a certain orbit and you
take the satellites you have them
approach each other and they come into
contact and dock with each other which
means they achieve full locking
connection
they become one and then you can have a
passage between the two satellites or
whatever right uh so that that's
something that you usually do uh with
space capsules which contain humans so
if you have let's say a so capsule or a
Dragon capsule of SpaceX it wants to and
you put humans in that and they you
launch them into space and you're
sending them to the International Space
Station this capsule will have to
eventually locate the space station
align perfectly with the docking port of
the space station and slowly gently make
a very non structive and and soft uh
docking and and proper docking with the
uh space station and once it is docked
properly and it is the docking the the
it is locked in place then you can open
the hatch and you can have the
astronauts enter or exit the space
station or the capsule it's very
important we are able to do this and
this is something the Americans and the
the
Russians perfected in the 1950s and 60s
and we are now trying to do that so I
hope it's successful hopefully it's
already succeeded um let me see let me
Google it and see if it succeeded right
let's let's let's find out uh ISRO
docking um let's see ISRO docking has it
happened or is it about to
happen Okay ISR space docking experiment
scheduled for January 7 today is January
4 okay three more days to go the Spade X
experiment okay I I hope it
succeeds uh because eventually if you
want to send people to
space and you want to have your own
space
station then the vehicle that takes the
people to
space it's going to be a capsule
attached to a rocket the rocket will
eventually uh detach from the capsule
and the capsule needs to know how to
make its way to the space station and
dock so that's very important for uh
that KN how the technology is very
important for us to develop right now if
we want to have a space station by 2035
which is like 10 years from now so yeah
I hope it suceeds and I'm glad we are
taking this initiative it's good why are
we planning to have our own space
station because we should have space
capabilities it's very important space
exploration is is very important from a
national development perspective from a
geopolitical perspective as well the two
or three countries that will lead the
world in space exploration in the 20th
21st century are the two or three
countries that will actually be ruling
the world so it's very important we do
this and that's why we doing
that PR Paul says uh RT reports that
Russia plans to deliver a nuclear power
plant to the Moon by 2033 35 and there
are claims of a joint China Russia
venture for resource and territory
claims on the Moon by 2050 meanwhile
Elon Musk reacted with interesting
sparking Western media Panic I'm not
sure there was a panic but okay uh can
China and Russia truly collaborate in
space while maintaining nuclear
standoffs on Earth how is the US likely
to perceive and respond to this
development okay uh yes so uh the
Russians are planning to uh to set up a
nuclear power plant on the Moon by the
mid
2030s and China is uh participating in
this Venture and so is India India is
also part of this the this
thing so it's interesting that Elon Musk
says that he is completely bypassing the
moon and going straight for Mass Mars he
isn't interested in right now in uh
setting up a colony or anything on the
moon he wants to go straight forward for
Mars and on the other hand Nations like
India Russia China and the
US are planning to have uh missions to
the
moon but Elon Musk obviously is a US
citizen and his company Space X is at
The Cutting Edge of the US geopolitical
initiative in space so the US is
actually targeting the moon as well as
Mars through Elon Musk they're targeting
Mars and through NASA they'll be
targeting the Moon
but when it comes to India to India
Russia China we are taking baby steps
India has uh last year or some something
we succeeded in touching down softly on
the moon chandran 3 right uh the Chinese
have have perfected that technology over
the past decade and and a half the
Changi Expeditions they've even done
sample return missions so the Chinese
are ahead of Russia and India Russia was
trying to uh land on the moon before
Chandra Anri but there
Lander sadly very unfortunately crashed
so he didn't didn't succeed so India and
China have the ability to land on the
moon successfully softly not a hard
Landing not a crash landing but a
controlled
landing and Russia has and and all three
are nuclear powers and we all have
nuclear technology so it it makes sense
for us to collaborate the Russians know
how to miniaturize nuclear reactors the
Chinese also know that we India we are
working on that so it makes sense for
the three nations to collaborate it's
not a place where we are competing we
don't have any overlapping interest on
the moon it's a completely uh open
territory so why not collaborate on this
matter instead of competing right so
India China
Russia uh it's a kind of joint venture
that we will be working on hopefully uh
so why a nuclear reactor it's not about
nuclear weapons it's about power it's
about Power
Generation Um you go to the
Moon how do you have enough power to
sustain life
right you need to power your batteries
you need to power your oxygen generators
and and purifiers air purifiers you need
to power you need to have heat on on on
on the Moon the Moon is a very and you
need to have cold when required because
the Moon is an extreme environment very
high temperatures and low temperatures
depending on whether it's day or night
so and and if you want to have humans on
the moon you need to be able to do this
you need a good steady reliable source
of power and you can depend on on solar
panels uh but 14 days there's no
sunlight so then you will need batteries
so why not put a nuclear power plant
there and take care of everything and
there's enough water on the moon to well
to be part of the power plant so it
makes sense to have a nuclear power
plant on the moon so that's why the
three nations are coll collaborating the
US will be watching this with a great
amount of interest and maybe some amount
of
concern because the US wants to
be um on
top when it comes to every single match
matter so because it makes sense for
them to do that they are uh the sole
superpower and they want to retain their
hegemony in all matters so they'll be
watching this with a lot of interest and
some amount some amount of
concern okay the Flying Saucer says what
are my views on Elon Musk insulting the
president of Germany and the chancellor
on X or Twitter and promoting a farri
party as reported the German media
uh yes it's interesting it's interesting
Elon Musk is currently actively involved
in the politics of multiple countries he
has done this Visa V Germany he has he's
look you could say that Elon Musk is a
private citizen and every private
citizen has the right to uh Express
their opinions sure but Elon Musk is not
a mere private citizen and he's no mere
ordinary person he's the wealthiest man
on the planet and he's one of the most
powerful people in the world
today now people will say that he's
wealthy not powerful power and wealth
don't correlate wealth doesn't mean
power and so on but Elon Musk has Ure
that he is now in a position of great
power by aligning by aligning himself
with the US geopolitical
interest if you want to be powerful in a
nation all you have to do is to align
yourself first of all be very wealthy
and then align yourself with the
nation's geopolitical interest and
geopolitical objectives and geopolitical
activities that automatically makes you
powerful because the powerful because
the power center of the nation will
then favor
you so Elon Musk I would say is now not
just influential not just wealthy but
also powerful maybe even more powerful
than the US president possibly and now
when he says and he's the guy who owns X
and when he says things about the
internal matters of various countries
that has a very big impact so he's
promoting he he's promoting various
political parties his favored political
parties in other nations that one could
argue could amount to us interference in
the internal affairs of that Nation but
that's no big deal because it always
happens the Americans have always been
interfering in the internal affairs of I
Nations so Elon Musk is right now
actively uh participating let's say in
the politics of VAR of multiple Nations
one is Germany
secondly I'm not sure about Canada but
definitely the
UK definitely the UK but and and he
has gone all out against uh the current
prime minister of the UK who deserves it
I would say he was the crown president
cutor he was the crown precut he was the
head of the crown prosecution service or
whatever it's called at the time when
they were covering up what was happening
in rham and those grooming that grooming
epidemic that probably still exists in
the UK and that sort of things so that
gu is a
complete crook K starmer and Elon Musk
is going after him but you could say
he's interfering in the internal affairs
of the UK so Elon Musk is is actively
involved in the politics of multiple
Nations my question is when is he going
to get involved in the internal affairs
of
India and are we going to allow that to
happen if he chooses to do that so yeah
interesting times social media is is
becoming a tool of has has long become
long ago become a tool of uh election
interference and interference in the
internal affairs of M of of Nations and
it can even U affect the results of
elections as we know quite well
here okay Krishna says Krishna is from
Nepal since the US
has since okay this is a question from
Krishna from Nepal since the US now has
two proxies Pakistan and Bangladesh to
combat India and Nepal also has a
significantly long border with India and
the US also knows this and here in Nepal
the government seems to be inclined
towards China yes how do you see Nepal
being uh interest of India China and the
us all top nations are are we doomed is
Nepal doomed is the question interesting
question from a nepales perspective so
let's do a thought experiment let's
assume that every nation is selfish and
doesn't care about Nepal okay let's
assume that the US doesn't care about
Nepal India doesn't care about Nepal
China doesn't care care about Nepal all
these countries only care about their
self-interest in Nepal is simply a
geopolitical Pawn on the chessboard for
these nations let's assume that okay I'm
not saying it's a truth but let's assume
it let's see it from the worst worst
case scenario perspective so what
happens so right now the situation is
that yes the US
is uh it it now has two wasal two
proxies in the subcontinent East and
West Pakistan Pakistan and Bangladesh
Pakistan is West Pakistan Bangladesh is
East Pakistan and they are conducting uh
the whole Civil War proxy war in uh
Burma and they're trying to create an
artificial Christian Nation out of
Indian Territory and burmes territory
and Bangladesh territory they want an
island which belongs to Bangladesh to
create an Air Force Base or whatever and
so on so forth they're doing all
this the US also has its fingers in
Nepal there is this power project that
they are uh involved in and there is
Christian conversion activities that the
Americans are doing directly or
indirectly Nepal lots of nepales are
getting converted to Christianity right
so the US is doing that in in Nepal
politically the nepales politicians seem
to be aligning with China it's it's a
fact yes there is a very strong
anti-india sentiment in nepales politics
if you want to win elections win votes
and be popular you have to say that
there is a big enemy in that's India and
then try to get favor from China and
that that's a game they've been playing
for a very long time uh Since U since
the downfall of the
napales monarchy very sad downfall of
the nepales
monarchy uh so the the king no longer
has any power the king who was the
father figure and who actually cared
about his subjects no longer is in power
and now you are at the mercy of
politicians in Nepal right and you are
no longer a Hindu rra now you are a
secular whatever Republic of sorts
whatever and the politicians are
inclined towards China now what does
China seek right now there seems to be a
Repro more of Kinds between in China and
India so if that happens if that
solidifies then Nepal will become less
of a
playground for geopolitical Intrigue
between the two Nations um but let's say
the Chinese and India are
still confrontational still adversaries
then the Chinese will seek to turn Nepal
into a Chinese vasal
State
now not not an occupied territory but a
vasal state Nepal will they will want
Nepal as a buffer zone between India and
Tibet so they will Nepal to be very
strongly Pro China they will want to
control of the politician in Nepal but
they will want Nepal to remain nominally
independent okay and the Chinese they
typically don't care what you do
culturally they will not try to destroy
your culture the Chinese won't do that
when it comes to Tibet they have imposed
Chinese culture language all that
because Tibet is an occupied territory
it's part of the Chinese Nation today
Nepal is not so they will not interfere
with your culture they don't care what
you do culturally as long as you're
politically in aligned with them the US
will not be will not be satisfied with
simply you being politically aligned
with the US they will want to destroy
your culture entirely and christianize
you because that's how you completely
control a people so that's the
difference between the US and China when
it comes from when it comes to India
India has a history of benign neglect
towards Nepal when King truan said that
I want to join India and make Nepal part
of India n said no no no not interested
right so and and and culturally and
demographically we are the same people
we know that uh but India has always
either had a policy of benign neglect
towards towards Nepal and sometimes
India has been harsh towards
Nepal there are I can remember at least
two instances of India blockading Nepal
and that I would say forced Nepal to
turn to China so I you cannot say that
India is not at fault is entirely
blameless and the nepales are to blame
for wanting to align with China Chinese
have never blockaded Nepal India has
done that at least twice including once
in the not too far away
past
uh so uh that's the situation when it
comes to People to People connections
India and Nepal with the same people the
nepales people and the Indian people can
travel without visas to each others
countries and we have an open border and
nepales people are more than welcome in
India you can live your whole life here
you have the right to serve in the
Indian Armed Forces which nobody else
gets which says that we trust you and we
we see you as our our own people uh so
that's that's a civilizational
connection um so I would not say Nepal
is doomed if Nepal is aligned with India
Nepal won't be doomed if Nepal is
aligned with China which is a different
culture not completely different but the
Chinese Communist Party culture is
different but if Nepal is aligned with
China it is not doomed but but you'll
become a puppet to a significant extent
of China and you'll able to tow the line
and all that and if you're align aligned
with the US you will end up losing your
identity so these are the choices you to
make uh I am perfectly happy Nepal
remaining independent and being on the
best of terms with India and I think
that would be the best for the nepales
people and of course they should the
people of Nepal the country of Nepal
should have the the right and the option
to to have any relation it wants with
any Nation it wants what's wrong with
that as a Sovereign Nation you have the
right to do that be friendly with China
be friendly with India be friendly with
the US be friendly with everybody if you
wish uh from my perspective I would say
don't align yourself with Nations that
that are India's adversaries but at the
end of the day it's your
choice Rohan
says as you have mentioned many times
when one superpower sees the rise of
another the former will do everything it
can to hinder the progress of the latter
yeah suide is trap it will seek to
destroy the latter now hypothetically if
Russia had won the Cold War and become
the sole superpower would Russia have
had what would have would Russia have
hindered India's rise the way the US
does in reality or would the good
relations between India and Russia be
Anor to the laws of geopolitics and and
they would even Aid us in our progress
very interesting question a hypothetical
speculative question but very
interesting nonetheless so we know that
the US is the sole superpower and they
see India as a nation that could become
a Challenger in 20 30 years maybe a
small time Challenger medium Challenger
not a complete challenger but yes and
they don't want that to happen they
don't want any Challengers potential
Challengers to even emerge on the
horizon and that's why they that's why
the relationship between the between
India and the US is very fraught right
now the us is going not exactly all out
but it's doing a lot to to hamper
India's uh growth uh so many examples
you know jet and the refusal to the
delay of in in delivering jet engines
significant delay despite having a
contract despite having signed a
contract and so on um so many
things I just give one example so the US
uh is kind of going after India and they
don't want to see India grow uh and and
reach its potential that's that much is
very clear right what if Russia was the
sole
superpower so if Russia was in the
position that the US is in
today how would it have
behaved when it see when it saw that
India is a growing Nation India is let's
say a rising nation and it could become
a great nation in the future would they
also do the same would they also behave
in the same way that's a very
interesting question would they also
have done that I I think there a
fundamental difference in the mindset
culturally and mentally psychologically
between the mindset of the US in the in
the Russians you know Nations as as an
entity a nation as an entity has a
character and a personality and a
psychology and a
psyche and Nations differ from each
other like two people differ from each
other
and the
US perspective on things is very
different from the Russian perspective
of things the way the US does things is
very different from how the Russians do
things so um if the Russians were the
sole superpower and there was a rising
India they would ask themselves is India
a competitor is India an adversary or a
rival to Russia and we have never been
Rivals we have always cooperated so they
would have said okay fine this country
doesn't seek to destroy us it doesn't
see seek to replace us it simply seeks
to rise to its fullest
potential but if you look at histo if
you look at history if India Rises to
the fullest extent of it of its
potential it becomes the greatest
economy in the world the largest economy
in the world which India was
historically for the longest amount of
time that would be a long-term threat
for Russia because when you have the
largest economy in the world you become
a military power the largest power and
then you can become a threat so Russia
would also seek I would imagine in that
situation to hamper India's rise it
would also seek to do that but will it
take the same approach the Americans are
taking the Americans seek to fragment
India the Americans seek to balkanize
India and one of the best ways of doing
it is to do demographic and religious
re-engineering of the population on an
industrial Mass scale so the Americans
use Christianity as a geopolitical tool
as a tool of of of interference right
Christian
conversions the Russians would not do
that the Russians would simply try to uh
maybe influence elections and get their
favorite political party in power a
political party that is not ambitious
and a leader who is not ambitious and
who will take India on a middle path
rather than a great path that's what the
Russians would do they would they would
have ensured that they will interfere in
the internal politics of
India and they would cultivate politics
part they would have cultivated
political parties and made sure that
such political parties are allowed to
come to power who are completely aligned
with Russia and who will not have huge
Ambitions of making India into a
superpower so India will a middle kind
of power and a power middle power that
is completely align aligned with Russia
in which case it's a great tool it's
it's a great Ally to have so that's the
approach the Russians would have taken
they would not have tried to
christianize India and Destroy India's
demographics that's not the approach the
Americans take the Americans seek to
balcon IE India and to re-engineer the
religious demographics of India and to
create artificial Nations out of Indian
ter territory and so on the Russians
would not have done that very different
approaches and it boils down to a
nation's character its personality it
its psyche its culture very different
cultures so that's what I think would
have
happened Mr Mr 88 says how do these
missionaries convert people or a group
of people forcibly to Christianity I
mean you once said that these converted
people become Internationals and become
loyal they develop extr territorial
loyalties which means loyalty to the
foreign
powers but how exactly does this process
play out in such a way that the person
literally abandons the nation's culture
customs values and
traditions look
missionaries uh they don't convert
people
forcibly the purpose of a missionary is
to convert people without using Force
that's what missionaries typically do in
today's world historically missionaries
like St St so-called St Patrick who
Paton s sa of Ireland they indulged in
cultural destruction and all kinds of
arm twisting activities and whatnot you
know brutal tactics to convert entire
populations today it's all whitewashed
and they made to look like one single
guy coming and convincing the whole of
Ireland to S overnight become Christian
you know that sort of thing is that's
the portrayal today um when it came to
the the spread of Christianity in Europe
it was done brutally by force read the
book uh what's the book he so many books
I can't remember the name the darkening
age by Katherine Nixie and she tells you
how it happened brutality it was done by
force
uh the northern Crusades and the
destruction of of uh the old Indo
European religion in various parts of
Europe all done brutally but in today's
world when the Christian missionaries go
to Africa when they go to India they go
to Nations they they seek out population
groups that are
impoverished dis uh impoverished and and
uh economically backward and they they
target those groups first so there is
this called the J let's let's Google it
shall we Joshua
project josua
project
um jhua project so this is a missionary
this is um an initiative that seeks to
christianize the world okay so yeah see
India is very important there India
let's let's see what they have to say
about India number of people groups 2272
they have categorized 2,27 22 groups out
of which they said that uh about 2,000
something are
unreached unreached by them by
Christianity progress level is very bad
unreached population largest religion
the evil Hinduism Christian adance they
say are 2.22% which is a
lie Evangelical annual growth rate is
only 4% globally it's 2.6 oh my God
they're doing well in
India and uh Udu language and they will
typically go after these you know
um uh people
uh these these uh either tribal people
or people who who live as Nomads or
people who uh suffer from poverty and so
on and they will give them inducements
to convert to Christianity various kinds
of inducements let's see States let's
let's take a look at for example Manipur
what does the Joshua Project have to say
about Manipur uh Buddhist 2% Christian
39.8% Hindu 43% that is according to the
2011 census which is which is a lie now
if you look at uh various look at how
many ethnic groups they have identified
in
Manipur okay now CI chin
is uh let's go to
the m okay even among the M they have
multiple groups M Manipur Muslim m
chhatria m Tanga mate unspecified let's
look at the mate unspecified what does
they say about the mate the unique
feature is that blah blah blah blah blah
what are their beliefs what are their
needs the M people need the chance to
allow Jesus Christ to bless them far
above what they can ever
imagine and so
on and there are scripture prayers for
the mate and specified in India and what
not okay there you high okay this is
enough I'm not going to do more of this
so the point is they don't seek to
convert people by force they seek to
convert people by either tricking them
or by giving them Financial other
inducements let's say you convert to
Christianity then you can identify
yourself as a as as a minority then the
government of India will give you
inducements they will give you
reservations and these people will also
give you various kinds of inducements
and all that it used to be earlier just
sacks of rice but now there are other
more sophisticated inducements that they
give you so it's it's a multipronged
approach the government of India helps
them a lot because if you become a
Christian then you get reservations and
all kinds of things uh you can identify
as minority you get certain rights that
only Christians or minorities get and
Hindus don't get uh so there are all
these incentives that the government of
India itself gives to convert out of
Hinduism and that helps the missionaries
but if they go to other nations they
will find other challenges and they seek
to do this without using
Force so let's say you are in a nation
that is very poor very low capita GDP
low per capita GDP and these guys tell
you then you convert to Christianity you
give up an old culture and we will
ensure that you have enough food your
children go to school we'll we'll
construct a school and we will allow
only kids of families who have converted
to come to the school and once you once
your kid grows up we will ensure that
they get a job in the government because
the government is also captured by them
and we'll ensure that you never have to
go hungry all those things they will
tell you so they will happily convert
just to ensure that your family survives
right so this is something that they are
able to do because of poverty they did
the same thing in Japan in China the
Chinese called them rice Christians
those who converted for the sake of the
grain the bags of rice and so on and so
on so so that's how it happens and
um so once you once you convert and you
are completely under the control of
these people you will develop loyalty to
them because you will tell yourself you
will you will imagine that you know what
my country didn't take care of me my
people my rulers didn't take care of me
but these white saviors or whoever they
are
they have ensured that I get what I
really deserve so why should I not be
loyal to them that's how it is played
out that's how it is done and that's
happening right now in the subcontinent
in especially in India and in Nepal
they've done that all over the world the
whole of Africa is either Muslim or
Christian very little of the original
culture survives they've done that in
Southeast Asia especially in the hill
regions the so-called mards of of
Cambodia Laos Etc were all converted the
various tribes that live the tribal
people who live in Burma the so called
cookies and whatnot all of them have
been converted 100 years ago they did
the same in nagaland various other parts
of in of far east of India over the
past seven eight decades and it's it's a
process that's ongoing their their
objective is to ultimately convert the
Hall of India to Christianity
Arjun sinna says what is the Timescape
model and why do why are people
predicting that this model will end the
dark mat the Dark Matter
Theory okay Timescape so Timescape
doesn't it's not about dark matter it's
about Dark Energy so first of all what
is dark energy dark energy is this
energy that is hypothesized to permeate
SpaceTime Across the Universe and it is
this mysterious Force or
substance that is believed to be behind
that is believed to be the driving
factor of the expansion of the universe
the accelerating expansion of the
universe okay that's dark energy and
dark energy accounts for roughly 70% of
the mass energy composition of the
universe about 24 25% is dark matter
which is a different thing and whatever
we see all the Luminous matter is about
four four and a half 5% of the universe
roughly very roughly I'm telling you now
what is this time scape model so so this
this model of dark energy all that is
the Lambda CDM model the standard model
of
physics now the time scape model is a
new Theory it's a groundbreaking
cosmological Theory and it challenges
the existence of dark energy and it
offers an alternative explanation for
The observed exp exp observed expansion
of the universe which is accelerating
expansion of the universe now this was
this theory was developed by researchers
in New Zealand at the University of
Canterbury I believe and it's a whole
different interpretation of cosmic
structure in evolution so the
standard model of physics the standard
Lambda cold Dark Matter Lambda CDM model
says that the Lambda CDM model assumes a
smooth and uniformly expanding universe
but the Timescape model takes into
account the granularity or lumpiness of
cosmic structure we know that the
Universe the actual universe is not
smooth we know there is lumpiness there
is granularity there are
large areas of of space that are empty
then you have galaxies which are very
lumpy in nature a lot of matter there
you have Galaxy
superclusters and there are voids so the
universe is not
smooth it is Lumpy so the time Cape
model takes into account this lumpiness
of uh Cosmic structure so it essentially
is acknowledging the existing of Galaxy
clusters and filaments and the voids
that come in between these and so on so
according to this model so we know we
have general relativity which has
effects like in special relativity which
has which has effects like time dilation
and length contraction and all that
relativistic effects so the the time
skape model says that gravitational
fields affect the rate of the passage of
time
differently in various re regions of the
universe in regions of the universe in
areas of the universe where you have
higher matter concentration like Galaxy
clusters and super clusters time passes
more slowly compared to Cosmic voids
which are which are mostly empty of
matter and because of these time
dilation effects uh Cosmic expansion
cannot be uniform that's what the
Timescape model suggests so in the
regions of the universe where you have
voids no mass or very little Mass over
there time passes faster and these
regions experience more expansion over
billions of years compared to areas of
the universe which are matter
dense so this model it uh it says
essentially that uh dark energy is an
illusion it says that the perceived EX
eration of the universe's expansion is
actually an illusion caused by the
uneven passage of time across the cosmos
very interesting uh Theory and by
accounting for this irregular
distribution of matter and the effect it
has on the passage of time the Timescape
model can explain the observed Cosmic
acceleration without invoking the
concept of dark
energy now do we have any uh any
evidence that supports the time scape
model so uh there was an analysis that
was done of about 1,500 type 1 a
supernovas and this is called the
pantheon Plus data set and this analysis
of this data set suggests that the
Timescape model fits observational data
slightly better than the standard Lambda
CDM model so there seems to be evidence
in favor of the Timescape model and
that's why it's it's it's vincing so
much interest of late so the the time
skape model resolves potentially
resolves various anomalies and tensions
in the current uh model and in the
current cosmological observations I'm
not sure if it resolves the Hubble
tension problem but it seems to be doing
a better job than the Lambda CDM model
so it's a very promising model but
further research and observational data
and all that need is needed to fully
validate this model and if it does
happen it could potentially
revolutionize our understanding
understanding of the universe's
expansion and its structure and the way
time passes in various parts of the
universe
okay
um many more questions let's let's take
some
uh uh okay ultimate power says how to be
articulate so what does it mean to be
articulate to be articulate means you
are able to
express your thoughts
with breadth with depth with with Nuance
with context in in the best possible way
and to be articulate typically means
that you able to speak well so you
express you're able to express yourself
well verbally so how to be articulate is
the question right it's not just about
practice it's not just about going out
there and talking speaking in in public
and becoming better and better at
speaking even a salesperson is great at
speaking but are they articulate right
that's a question you to ask yourself to
be articulate first of all you need to
have original thoughts you need to have
original
thinking and it it shows when you speak
if you have original thinking so um how
to how to have original thinking is the
question now you can't TR be truly be a
real true original thinker if you simply
think and and you don't write to fully
develop your ideas and thoughts you have
to write writing is a process that
allows you to think deeper writing is a
tool that allows you to think better and
deeper it allows you to analyze your
thoughts in a way that you can't analyze
by simply thinking so the first
thing the first step you to take towards
becoming articulate is to start writing
down your thoughts and see what you've
written and analyzing that critically
and ask yourself is this is what I think
have I expressed myself
well
enough or can I express myself better or
can I think deeper and can I come up
with something better than this and then
you write it again and you write in a
better way and when you write these
things down the these things these ideas
and and thoughts and Concepts that
percolate deep into your mind so the
first step is to write your ideas down
have this practice have this develop
this habit of writing things down maybe
on a daily
basis that's the first step the second
step is to then articulate what you
write in words verbally and if you make
a habit of doing these two things first
writing things down as as well as you
can and secondly speaking these things
aloud from memory not not reading them
but from memory because you've already
thought it out properly and written it
down well so then you should be able to
speak it to to express it verbally as
well from memory without reading it if
you can do these things regularly on a
daily basis consistently over a period
of time then you will become better and
better at articulation and you will
become more articulate than before
that's the process it's a long process
nothing is simple nothing is easy there
are no shortcuts but this is how you do
it
okay photo here one Patel says across
many nations we see that men have short
hair and women have long hair why is the
modern Indian hairstyle so different
from our traditional Indian hairstyle as
we see Lord Ram Lord Krishna abijit chaa
have long hair
look I don't know why it's like that
it's it's strange isn't it that women
and
girls generally have long hair at least
shoulder length or whatever or longer
and boys and men typically have short
hair why is it so if you look at India's
historical sculptures and carvings of
men as well as women you see that both
have long hair so Indian men
historically traditionally used to have
long hair either shoulder length or or
more
how did we end up being the way we are
that most the vast majority of boys and
men have short hair it's just a custom
now I think we and you you see this in
the west as well historically in the
west I think at least the nobility and
the aristocracy of the Anglo-Saxon
people used to have long hair if you see
paintings of various people who
generally are are nobles and Aristocrats
you see you see long hair shoulder
length or
longer um I would imagine the
peasants the the unfortunate peasants
and the the the lower classes would have
had short hair because they used to
engage in manual labor and long hair
could be an impediment perhaps and maybe
maybe over time this thing spread to
everybody perhaps I'm I'm just guessing
I don't think anybody has done a
sociological analysis or a social
historical analysis of how
this practice of of men keeping short
hair
emerged but I get the feeling it came
from the the
West that's the feeling I get I'm not
really sure but it's an interesting
question you've asked uh so
traditionally Indian men and women both
had long
hair and somehow this practice came into
our our our our society and now it's
it's the it's a norm for men and boys to
have short hair I choose to Buck the
norm Buck the
trend all right okay let's take some
questions I I have many more questions
from the comments but let me take some
questions from the live chat from all my
viewers who are watching right now let
us see
uh okay okay let's take this question by
current does the existence of water in
solid or liquid form imply the existence
of Life on any Planet uh the there are
many planets on which
water probably exists planets or moons
we know water exists on Mars in in the
solid form we don't
uh we haven't seen too much evidence of
it being liquid maybe once or twice but
U it's mostly in the solid form Ice
Water Ice Martian polar regions and
under the
soil uh we know there's water on the
moon significant quantities of water on
the moon we know there is water on
various moons in the Jupiter and Saturn
moon
systems uh and so latus Europa there
could be a a water ocean subsurface
water ocean on Pluto as well could be so
there's plenty of places where water
exists does it imply that you have life
in these places on these on these
planets or moons it doesn't necessarily
mean there is life but if there is
liquid water you would say that I would
say that there's a higher chance of
earthlike
Life existing there earthlike in some
like microorganisms or something like
that that's a higher chance of uh life
that we kind of understand the life life
the kind that we understand
of of it existing there but it doesn't
guarantee that life is there
okay all right uh other questions other
questions uh anshit says will Canada
merge into the US in the upcoming
future it could happen if Mr Donald
Trump decides that this will happen and
there's little the Canadians can do to
stop this from happening they don't have
any armed forces of their own and
they have a bad government a bad
system um maybe it's it's maybe they'll
be better off being one of the one of
the states of the United States maybe
the 51st state or maybe multiple states
of Canada becoming part of the
us so if you look at the if you look at
Canada Canada today you have what states
do you have provinces Alberta saskat
chovan um Alberta sasan Quebec of course
and whatever else three four territories
I can think of right now maybe these
could become American states or maybe
Canada could become a territory like
Puerto Rico and so on it could happen if
Trump decides that it should happen and
if it happens maybe it's good for the
Canadians okay hsh Bagel says I have a
theory that that an atom has a world in
itself okay interesting Theory please if
if you think this is a viable Theory
please develop it mathematically
because science is all about mathematics
everybody has ideas everybody has
theories but if you want to pursue the
theory to its logical conclusion you
have to develop a mathematical model
that incorporates what we know of the
universe and
then and then through that model you try
to see if your theory or idea does it
uh uh is it a is it compatible with both
with what we already know of the
universe so so it's nice to have a
theory and I'm glad that you thinking
along these lines and trying to think
differently but to to Really develop the
theory you have to develop a
mathematical a mathematical model of
this Theory so I'll be happy if you do
that and I'll be happy to see
it okay um South Korea have no okay Mr
88 says thoughts of South Korea
situation they re recently impeached
their acting president what is the Deep
State planning doesn't matter look uh no
disrespect to South Korea but the South
Kore but South Korea is not a very
important Nation it's it's first of all
it's not a Sovereign Nation it's under
permanent US military occupation just
like Japan is uh dozens of permanent US
military bases on South Korean
territory um and
they are not that significant
geopolitically so um so I have not
really been following what's happening
in South Korea I I was I was about to
take a plane I was about
to take off on a flight when I heard the
news that this uh coup had happened the
South Korean president had done a coup
an auto coup it was a 5 and a half hour
flight and by the time I landed I once I
landed I found out the coup had failed
so it was a very brief coup and looks
like uh the guy has now been
impeached it it makes no
difference look it doesn't matter who is
ruling South Korea whether it's Mr X or
Mr y or Miss Z it doesn't matter at the
end of the day the South Korean
government is going to behave the same
it is permanently and completely aligned
with the objectives of the US it doesn't
matter who is the acting or non-acting
president whether there's a president or
a dictator or this democracy or
autocracy doesn't matter at all it's a
nation whose sole existence is to serve
us geopolitical interests in the region
so that's that's what matters and once
you understand that you don't care
anymore about what happens internally
politically it doesn't matter it's all
managed right let's see some more
questions okay Amisha asks an
interesting question do you think aliens
will understand the golden record so
what she's asking is this let's let's go
to Google and let's it's the Voyager
golden record that's what she's asking
about uh
Voyager golden
record let's put that on the
screen um this
is the so these are photograph
photograph records that were included
about let's take a look at uh what NASA
has to say the golden record so the
Voyager spacecraft were launched in 197
27 they car carry a unique Time Capsule
along with them into inter Interstellar
space and um Dental metal plaques
identify the time and place of origin
for the benefit of other space farers
that might find them in the distant
future uh intend a time capsule intended
to communicate the story of our world
two
extraterrestrials a phonograph Record 12
in goldplated Copper disc containing
sounds and images see Ed to identify the
diversity of life and culture on the
earth natural sounds thunder birds
musical sections blah blah blah and so
on so that's the record and there's the
cover the the protective cover includes
instructions for playing its contents
finding Earth in the
cosmos and dating how long it's it has
been in space okay and I think they have
tried to make it as universally
intelligible as possible to anybody who
can who can find it anybody who is
intelligent enough so first of all
you're assuming that whoever in the
distant future finds this will be
intelligent enough to be able to
understand it which means that it will
have to be understood by the scientists
of the extraterrestrials not the artists
and the the
YouTubers scientists right um so I
think uh they they must have asked
themselves this this question and they
must have thought long and hard as to
what to put in the record and what to
put on the cover the instructions and
other message and uh I've not really
looked into what how to decipher this
I've I've I know about it but I don't
know what the methodology is so I'm
assuming that they've done a good job of
this and hopefully whoever finds it in
the distant future maybe a few million
years from today hopefully they'll be
able to decipher it and by the time if
they figure out how to reach Earth
hopefully it's no longer a threat
because we hopefully by the time we'll
have evolved into a much better
technologically more advanced
civilization
um okay what else do we have
uh Sergeant Skyland says does India have
its own fifth generation fighter jet we
don't the best fighter J that we have
the most advanced one that we have is
the Rafal which is classified as a 4.5
generation fighter plane which is which
means that it is a fourth generation
fighter plane with some features that we
would expect to have in a fifth
generation fighter plane so the Rafal is
the best we have we are developing a
fifth generation fighter plane fighter
jet called the amca the advanced medium
combat
aircraft uh the first test the first
test flights will happen in the early
2030s maybe maybe before that hopefully
maybe the late
2020s and it's scheduled to come into
production sometime in the 2030s maybe
the first half of the 2030s so we are
developing it and the major impediment
is the the jet engine so that's
something I've discussed before so I'm
not going to go to it today but India
doesn't have a fifth generation fighter
plane okay
um Von asks are chess Grand Masters
great at
math uh interesting they generally
should be because math is what is math
at the end of the day it's abstract
representation of logic just pure
logic uh in in symbolic form so and and
chess is all about logic it's all about
logic and thinking ahead and finding
patterns and calculating things and all
so I would say math chess Grand Masters
should be good at math excuse
me but it's not necessary that just that
you take a random chess grandmas it's
not necessary that they would have had
an education in math which would which
indicates that many chess Grand Masters
may not be that good at math simply
because they haven't learned it or they
haven't been taught it but you take a CH
Grandmaster and teach them math I think
they could be probably among the one
person of mathematicians so I would say
that if you are a CH Grandmaster it
means that you have that logical
thinking capability that is needed for
being a great Ma for being a good
mathematician so yes it means that you
have the the
skills if it means that you have the
aptitude for being gred
math all
right
uh curen says how to become rich without
being an entrepreneur uh either you can
be born into great wealth or you can
become a
bureaucrat um if you are a bureaucrat
there are means and ways of becoming
really rich really fast I'm talking
about India or you become a
politician and once you're a politician
a few Crow Rupees is
nothing apart from that I can't think of
any way of becoming rich without
becoming an entrepreneur um you will
never become genuinely
Rich uh by doing a 9 to-5 job or being
by doing a job by having a salary a
salary can never make you rich you need
to or you could become an investor and
be good at the stock market but it's
very dangerous it's very dangerous and
it's very easy to lose all your money in
the stock market so I would not advise
that the the
cleanest and safest way not safest but
the cleanest way of doing it is by
becoming a business person an
entrepreneur by opening a business
maybe and it's very hard to do business
okay it's it's it's very easy to fail
and lose money so it's all about
risk so you have to take essentially you
have to take risks to become
rich and for that you have to be a
business person or an entrepreneur
otherwise you take the safe way and
become a bureaucrat or a
politician even then you have to have
some Talent obviously at
that mcloven says are you aware of the
Chinese credit course score system yes
people can't buy basic amenities if
their credit scores are low can this be
the future of cashless economies it's
kind of distopian it's kind of if you
implement it right it could be good also
right uh VC China as an authoritarian
society and the credit Cod system
essentially gives you points and demerit
points for your actions so if you have a
spotless record you have indulge in no
criminal activities then you will have a
good credit score if you pay your taxes
on time if you do everything as per the
law you will have a great credit score
but if you are a person who has a
criminal record you may have a low
credit score if you uh if you are
anti-national if you if you have
tendencies that are that do not align
with your na nation's interest you will
get a bad bad credit score and then you
can't do a lot of things you can't
travel by plane or train or whatever
simply your face your face is your
identity and they can recognize your cre
they can deduce
so they have these systems that identify
your face and then from your face they
will know what your credit score is so
it can be very very bad if it is done in
an authoritarian society that is anti-
people but it can be great if it is
implemented in a society that is
genuinely Pro people so it all depends
so this could be the future of cashless
economies the Americans are also they
also seem to be of the path of adopting
something like
that um yeah so it it can be be great it
can be terrible as well depends on who
implements it like all
Technologies okay Raji gun says why did
the aoms never try to rule the rest of
India apart from the
Northeast
um to be able to
rule territories
depends first of all on your ambition
and secondly on your
capabilities so
maybe so I either you did not have the
ambition or may or otherwise maybe you
did not have the capabilities so every
Um Kingdom has a certain
amount of of
ability depending on how much resources
it has at its disposal and what's the
quality of its Manpower in infantry and
in military depending on that it will be
capable of of conquering and ruling a
certain amount of territory the Mongols
they in during the time of chingis Khan
had essentially unlimited potential they
had developed tactics and strategies and
ways and means of doing things that
nobody else had they so that's why they
were able to conquer half of the entire
Known World at the time there are other
kingdoms that never expanded much so the
aams they ruled a significant area of
the Far East of
India um but maybe there were some
limitations which
which meant that they were not able to
expand further beyond that I am I have
not studied aam history in great detail
so I would not be able to give you the
details but if if uh a kingdom doesn't
expand Beyond a certain area it means
that there are limitations that is
facing either material limitations
Manpower limitations quality of the
military limitations or simply that the
rulers don't have the ambition to rule
beyond that area could be one of
multiple factors that's what that's what
I could say
okay feminist Slayer says how to become
strong when your when one parent is
alive and near death bed death bed I'm
feeling extremely angry and sad at the
same
time well I'm very sorry to hear that
you're going through this very sorry to
hear this uh it's unfortunately see
unfortunately there's nothing you can do
about the situation uh that is something
that every person unfortunately sadly
has to go through it is it is what goam
Buddha said right
that life is suffering well life doesn't
need to be all suffering but there is
suffering involved in life as you grow
older you will lose things you will lose
friends you will lose family you will
eventually if you live long enough
unfortunately lose your parents that's
just uh the way life goes for everybody
and the older you get the more you lose
you know that's how it is sadly uh and
yeah it's natural to feel sad angry
frustrated all of that it's natural to
feel that way and I'm sorry you're
feeling this
way um how to deal with this how to cope
with
this well
um I don't know what to say how do you
cope with this you have to accept it as
a fact of life and you have to tell
yourself that it's not that the gods are
against you it's not that the world is
against you and you are being singled
out for this treatment every single
person who has lived has gone through
this and every single person at the end
of the day one day will have to leave
this world there is nothing unique about
the situation unfortunately I know it's
it's terrifying it's terrible it's
terrible it's it's it's painful no doubt
about it but it's something everybody
unfortunately has to go through so you
would tell yourself that this is not
this is not different from what anybody
else has has undergone in the past and
there is life beyond this there is life
beyond this you see you you have a long
way to go I'm I'm guessing you're a
young person so you have a long life
ahead of you and there's a lot you have
to contribute to the world and to
yourself there's a lot you have to
experience got to you to contribute to
the to your family to the world and at
the end of the day from my perspective a
good life a meaningful life is a life in
which you end up contributing more to
society than you take from it and you
will encounter setbacks in life so uh
don't indulge in too much self-pity
which is which means that you feel sorry
for yourself and you sit in this
depressed and sad melancholic mood it's
okay to feel sad depressed but tell
yourself that I will do this for this
amount of time and after that I'll move
on that's how you be strong
so it's not about changing your mindset
in the way you think it's about changing
your behavior that okay I will give
myself this much time to feel sorry and
sad and to mourn but after this time
period is over I will go ahead with my
life go back to normal
whether I'm feeling sad or sorry inside
doesn't matter but I will behave like
I'm fine and through your actions and
behaviors you change your mindset
because if you behave like you're fine
and you behave everything is fine and
everything is under control eventually
your mind is forced to accept that and
that's the secret of being strong how do
you become strong mentally by simply
changing your behavior no matter how you
feel and you continue that pattern of
behavior for a certain amount of time
and your mindset automatically will
change with whether it likes it or not
that is the secret of strength changing
your behavior modifying your behavior no
matter how you feel so once again I'm
sorry to hear this and all the best to
you
sir uh
[Music]
okay let's see what else do we have uh
fox star gamer says what's your view on
the ongoing conflict between Pakistan
and Taliban it's it's natural um in 21
one or whenever it was the Taliban was
given Afghanistan by the Americans I
said at the time that Afghanistan is not
becoming is not going to become a
Pakistani asset Afghanistan is going to
become a problem for
Pakistan and that's exactly what's
happened the the two Nations have a big
territorial dispute Afghanistan claims a
large chunk of Pakistani territory that
goes back to the time to the the roote
of this conflict goes back to the 18
1800s and uh
the Afghans claim the whole of kber Paka
most of it as their territory and the
people of K pakun also seek to re to
reunite with Afghanistan so Pakistan has
a big headache on its hands and the
pakistanis have always treated the
Afghans the pons rather cruy and
brutally so there is this thing so I am
not surprised this thing and the problem
is that Afghanistan isn't strong enough
to
really hurt Pakistan too
much Pakistan has a professional Army
professional military they forget about
the nuclear weapons you don't those are
not uh pertinent to this conversation
but uh the Afghanistan has a Talib
Afghanistan has a Taliban and Talib the
Taliban is not a professional fighting
force it's a great guilla Warfare outfit
but not a professional military force
I'm sure they trying to they're trying
to professionalize their their their
military wing
but that'll take
time uh so uh when look when you look at
the balance of power the pakistanis are
way more powerful but the advantage the
Taliban has that the that the Afghans
have is that they have a huge Afghan
population within Pakistan and that's
why Pakistan recently deported I don't
know about a million plus
Afghans very cruy and brutally back to
Afghanistan and nobody said a word
across the world no human rights
apologists came and said that Pakistan
should not do
this so yeah this is an ongoing
situation it is it is going to remain an
ongoing
situation okay
um Pikachu gaming says what do you think
about this new virus in China and how
and and and does it affect India one
hears of a new virus that seems to be
doing the rounds in some parts of China
uh I don't know much about it right now
is it HPV or something human papiloma
virus or something I'm not sure which
virus it is
um I will obviously have to look at it
if it becomes a matter of
concern and all I can say is I
simply and very deeply hope that this
doesn't become another situation like
what we had a few years ago that's what
I can say I hope the Chinese can uh can
keep it under control and end the
issue yeah H hmpv virus okay okay so I'm
like I said I really haven't gone into
detail about this but maybe I'll have to
I hope I
don't okay
um okay let's take this question nikit
the ngv is aiming to replace the pslv by
the by the
2030s there is no chatter on a new super
heavy launch vehicle lvm when will our
government pour pour its resources into
such crucial projects I think only the
government can answer this question uh
it's very important for India to be a
major space Power otherwise we'll be
left completely behind and left and
become an afterthought
geopolitically and and the Nations that
have the ambition will go and take
control of entire other worlds like the
moon and Mars and uh we'll Simply Be
bystanders
so we have the talent we have the
engineering Talent the scientific Talent
at is RO to develop any kind of
Rocket
but for that they need orders from the
government they need approval
authorization from the government the
government gives them a certain amount
of funding for the projects that are
approved and it's sufficient for the
projects but there is no approval for
these projects like building more
powerful Rockets significantly more
powerful there are there is there are
these iterative changes is to the gslv
family A Rocket that's 10 time 10% more
powerful 15% more powerful I'm talking
about 10 times more powerful 50 times
more powerful that's the kind of rockets
we need even now sometimes we have to
launch satellites using Space X or Aran
Rockets why why do we need that why
can't we have a rocket that's 10 times
20 times 50 times more powerful than the
gslb why not why can't we reach the moon
in two days instead of three months or
whatever time it takes for the chandrian
3 or for the chandrian series we do
these slow orbit raising Maneuvers if
you have a Strong Enough Rocket powerful
enough rocket you'll reach the the moon
in three or four days or whatever less
than a week so we simply our political
class simply doesn't seem to have that
ambition and it's not like we don't have
the money but the money is being spent
in other things free bees for various
people who may or may not be deserving
of those freebies and so on anyway U
that's that's a question that only the
politicians can answer only the people
who rule the country can answer I
unfortunately cannot answer it if I had
a choice I would definitely ensure that
India would that that ISRO would be in
the process of developing much more
powerful rocket technology including
reusable Rockets but we're not even
doing that so that's where we
are okay on that note I'm going to end
this session it's once again cross 2
hours 13 minutes so thank you so much
for all all the questions apologies to
those of you those questions I could not
answer this time and I'll take many more
questions in next week's episode until
then take care keep asking questions and
as always keep raising your standards
thank you see you soon bye